Register of the Paul Lubeck Papers, 1950-1969
Hoover Institution Archives
Paul Lubeck Papers,
1950-1969
75093
Lubeck, Paul
5 manuscript boxes. (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, reports, clippings, and notes, relating to the trade union movement in Africa, primarily during the 1960s.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
Labor movement--Africa.; Trade-unions--Africa.; Africa.
Historical Note
These papers were accumulated, mainly during the 1960s, by William Friedland and Paul Lubeck in the course of academic research on trade unionism in Africa. In 1976 Paul Lubeck was an Assistant Professor of Sociology at the University of California at Santa Cruz. In 1962, when the research documented in the papers was being carried out, William Friedland was an Assistant Professor at the New York State School of Industrial Relations at Cornell University.
Abbreviations
IFPAAW International Federation of Plantation And Agricultural Workers
NUTA National Union of Tanganyika Workers
TANU Tanganyika / Tanzania African National Union
TAZARA Tanzania Zambia Railway
Series Description
- SUBJECT FILE, 1950-1969 (Box 1-5.)
  Conference reports, copies of internal documentation of trade union and government bodies, correspondence, drafts of papers and articles, publications, research notes and clippings, arranged alphabetically by subject.
Container List
- SUBJECT FILE
  - Africa
    - Francophone, 1962-1969 (Box 1., Folder 1)
    - North, 1964-1966 (Folder 2)
    - Algeria, 1962-1967 (Folder 3)
    - Cameroons, 1959-1968. (Folder 4)
      Contains Proceedings of the foundation congress of the Union Generale Des Travailleurs Du Kameroun, 1959
    - Congo, Brazzaville, 1960-1965 (Folder 5)
    - Congo, Kinshasa (Zaire), 1959-1968 (Folder 6)
    - Dahomey, 1962-1968 (Folder 7)
    - Ghana, economic development and protection for workers, 1965-1968 (Folder 8)
    - Ghana, miscellaneous, 1956-1966 (Folder 9)
    - Ghana, overthrow of Nkrumah by military, 1966 (Folder 10)
    - Ghana, parliamentary debates, 1958-1968 (Folder 11)
    - Ghana, politics, 1961-1968 (Folder 12)
    - Ghana, trade union education, 1966-1967 (Folder 13)
    - Ghana, trade unions, strikes and mergers and other matters, 1960-1969 (Folder 14)
    - Kenya, Mboya, Tom, (1956?)-1962 (Folder 15)
    - Kenya, miscellaneous, 1958-1963 (Folder 16)
    - Kenya, research notes, 1959-1965 (Folder 17)
    - Kenya, strikes, 1957-1968 (Box 2., Folder 1)
    - Kenya, strikes, 1965-1968 (Folder 2)
    - Kenya, trade unions and politics, 1960-1968. (Folder 3)
      Contains copy of agreement for the establishment of a National Joint Council between Federation of Kenya Employers and Kenya Federation of Labour, 1961
    - Kenya, trade unions in general, 1960-1969. (Folder 4)
      Contains Review of the trade union position in Kenya, Kenya Federation of Labour, 1962
    - Kenya, wage claims and disputes, 1962-1967 (Folder 5)
    - Liberia and Ethiopia, 1961-1968 (Folder 6)
    - Libya, 1965 (Folder 7)
    - Malawi, 1962-1966 (Folder 8)
    - Nigeria, miscellaneous, 1965-1968 (Folder 9)
    - Nigeria, research notes, 1957-1966 (Folder 10)
    - Sierra Leone, 1961-1968 (Folder 11)
    - South Africa, 1962-1968 (Box 3., Folder 1)
    - South West Africa, 1960-1966 (Folder 2)
    - Southern Rhodesia (Zimbabwe), 1962-1968 (Folder 3)
    - Tanzania (Tanganyika), control of trade unions by government and other matters, 1958-1967. (Folder 4)
    - Tanzania, five year plan and development and trade unions, 1962-1967 (Folder 5)
    - Tanzania, labor force survey report by Manpower Planning Unit, Ministry of Economic Affairs, Tanzania, (1965?) (Folder 6)
    - Tanzania, publications including statutes, 1950-1962. (Folder 7)
      Contains Tasks and Man Management of African Labour, Overseas Food Corporation, 1950
    - Tanzania, mutiny and riot of January 19 1964, 1964. (Folder 8)
      Contains 2 eyewitness reports.
    - Tanzania, NUTA (National Union of Tanganyika Workers), 1960-1967. (Folder 9)
      Contains unofficial translation of General Secretary's verbal report to first general meeting, 1965
    - Tanzania, NUTA, 1964-1967 (Folder 10)
    - Tanzania, NUTA, 1965 and undated. (Folder 11)
      Contains resolutions adopted by first conference, 1965 and Rules, undated
    - Tanzania, research notes on trade union leaders and trade unions, 1963 (Folder 12)
    - Tanzania, rural village settlement, 1963-1964 (Folder 13)
    - Tanzania, TANU (Tanganyika / Tanzania African National Union), 1963-1967 (Folder 14)
    - Tanzania, TANU / NUTA relations, 1967 (Box 4., Folder 1)
    - Tanzania, TAZARA (Tanzania Zambia Railway), 1967 (Folder 2)
    - Tunisia, 1965-1968 (Folder 3)
    - Uganda, trade unions, 1966-1968 (Folder 4)
    - Uganda, trade unions and politics, 1959-1968 (Folder 5)
    - Uganda, trade unions and strikes and economic development, 1960-1967 (Folder 6)
    - Zambia, miscellaneous, 1962-1968 (Folder 7)
    - Zambia, social and economic development, 1960-1968 (Folder 8)
    - Zambia, strikes, 1960-1968 (Folder 9)
    - Zambia, trade unions and politics, 1959-1968 (Folder 10)
    - Zambia, trade unions in general, 1964-1968 (Folder 11)
    - Zanzibar, 1962-1967 (Folder 12)
  - Bibliographic collecting activities of Professor Friedland at Cornell University, 1962 (Folder 13)
  - International Trade Union Organisations
    - African-American Labor Center, New York, 1962-1968. (Folder 14)
      Contains copy of IFPAAW (International Federation of Plantation And Agricultural Workers) report on trade union organisation in Nyasaland (Malawi), 1962
    - African Trade Union Confederation, 1962-1968 (Folder 15)
    - All-African Trade Union Federation, 1962-1966 (Folder 16)
    - All-African Trade Union Federation, 1964-1967 (Folder 17)
    - All-African Trade Union Federation / African Trade Union Confederation relations, 1962-1967 (Folder 18)
    - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, African Region, 1957-1967 (Box 5., Folder 1)
    - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, African Region, 1963-1964 (Folder 2)
    - Tettegah, John, Secretary-General of All-African Trade Union Federation, 1963-1966 (Folder 3)
  - Trade Unions
    - Africa, general, 1958-1968. (Folder 4)
      Contains report on Public Services International African conference, 1965 and drafts of articles by Charles A. Orr
    - Africa, general, 1967. (Folder 5)
      Contains report on African-American Labor Center conference, 1967
    - African Socialism and African trade unions, 1958-1967 (Folder 6)
    - African trade unions and government interference, 1961-1963 (Folder 7)
    - African trade unions, detention torture and execution of trade unionists, 1964-1966 (Folder 8)
    - African trade unions, education, 1963-1966. (Folder 9)
      Contains memorandum on subsequent careers of named individuals trained as trade union leaders